Welcome to Essential Hayek
欢迎来到哈耶克简要
I'm Don Boudreaux
我是Don Boudreaux
professor of economics at George Mason University
乔治梅森大学经济学教授
senior fellow with the Fraser Institute
弗雷泽研究所高级研究员
and blogger at Café Hayek
博客Café Hayek的博主之一
This video was part of the Fraser Institute initiative
本视频是由弗雷泽研究所制作的
to present the key ideas of F.A. Hayek in an easily accessible format
对哈耶克关键思想的通俗介绍
Hayek observed that the challenge of living in a modern society involves
哈耶克观察到在现代社会生活的挑战包含
two sets of very different interactions
两套非常不同的互动方式
those that occur among our family and friends
一种是与家庭和朋友打交道的方式
and those that occur in the external world
另一种是与外部世界打交道的方式
Let's simplify this rather complex idea with an example
让我们举例来说明这个复杂的想法
This is Tom
这是Tom
He owns a bicycle repair shop
他经营着一家自行车维修店
Tom repairs people's bikes
Tom修理顾客的自行车
and in return, his customers pay him
顾客则付给Tom钱作为回报
Tom is also married and a father
Tom也结婚了并已为人父
When Tom is at home with his family
Tom与家人在一块时
the interactions between his wife and children
一家人之间的互动
are very different from those in Tom's bike shop
与Tom自行车店里的互动非常不同
For example, if Tom's son needs his bike repaired
举个栗子，如果Tom的儿子自行车坏了
he simply asks Tom
他只需要跟Tom说一声就行了
We don't expect Tom to charge his son for the repair as he would a customer in store
我们并不认为Tom会像对顾客那样对儿子收费
Hayek observed that a family is not a market
哈耶克观察到家庭与市场不一样
and the rules of the market do not apply to the family
市场上的规则也不适用于家庭
As a father
作为一个父亲
Tom gains satisfaction from helping his son by repairing his bike
Tom从帮助他儿子修车中获得了满足
This satisfaction is different from the feelings he experiences with his customers
这种满足与他从顾客那所获得的感受不同
Almost all of them Tom doesn't know outside the work
几乎所有顾客Tom在工作外都不认识
Likewise, Hayek explained that society at large cannot operate like a family
类似的，哈耶克描述了大型社会是无法像个家庭那样运转的
If Tom treated his customers like his son
如果Tom像对待孩子那样对待顾客
and didn't charge them for fixing their bikes
为他们免费修理自行车
his business would soon go broke
他的生意很快就会难以为继
Hayek's point is that markets and economies would collapse
哈耶克认为如果我们试图让社会像个扩展大家庭那样运行
if we try to operate society at large as if it were one big extended family
市场和经济将会崩溃
Hayek identified a subtle, but key aspect of a society
哈耶克指出了一个社会微妙又关键的一面
which is that we're governed by two distinct sets of rules and constraints
即有两套不同的规则和约束作用于我们的行为
both function well within their own spheres
在它们各自的范围内都运行良好
but great disruptions and costs occur when we try to transplant one set of rules to the other sphere
但当我们把其中之一用于另一个的范围时，就会导致严重的破坏
To learn more and to download  for free
想要下载和更多了解《哈耶克简要》
visit www.essentialhayek.org
请访问www.essentialhayek.org
翻译 by tcya